Hello everyone and
welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco. Hi guys,
my name is Catherine and today
we have an upper
intermediate level lesson for you
about some very
interesting things. That's right.
Today we're gonna talk about
fortune tellers or people that
read your future. All
right, so if I want to know
who I will marry, if I will
be rich, I will go to this
fortune teller and she or he
will tell me what's in my future.
That's right. It's
very popular in many
cultures around the world,
many different ways of
reading your future or
telling you your future.
So let's jump into this dialogue
and see what's going on today.
Look at this newspaper article
about this famous local medium.
It says that she is really gifted in so
popular now that she's booked solid with
appointments for the next
12 months. You don't really
believe in all that hocus-pocus
mumbo jumbo, do you?
Well, I have had many
friends that went to a
psychic and got their
palms read and most of the
things the psychic
told them came true.
Of course it does. They tell
you general and obvious things
like that you'll be successful
or have a big house.
I think most of the times
they're just scam artists.
Well, historically it's
a practice that many
cultures share, reading the tarot cards and
the east they would even read tea leaves.
I even heard that there
are people that make
you smoke a cigar and
then read your ashes.
All superstitious
nonsense. I would still like
to go to one and see what he
or she has to say just for kicks.
Great. I'll make an appointment.
All right, we're back. So a
lot of interesting things here.
Let's take a look at
some of those words
on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
So in language takeaway today
we are focusing on some words
that describe fortune
telling but also the different
ways of doing so. The
first word we have is
actually a name for a person who
can read the future, right Marco?
That's right, a medium
in the dialogue.
We hear about a woman who
is a medium and is very talented.
Actually a medium is
interesting because a
medium is a person who can
communicate with the debt.
That's right. Or who can
communicate with the other side.
And if you think about middle, medium, I
mean the same thing. It's someone who is
in the middle of two
things and so a medium can
maybe transmit these
different ideas or signals.
Right, exactly. So it's
a person that basically
communicates as you say
with the dead or someone
that can listen to people
who are not here anymore.
But obviously they are
a type of person that
could also use this
gift to tell your future or
to have the people who
are dead to tell you what's
going to happen in
the future. That's right.
And so another kind of
person who would do something
similar is a psychic.
That's right. All right.
Now a psychic is a person who
generally will read your future for you.
We'll tell you the future.
Maybe the psychic will have
a special tool, like a crystal
ball. Just remember
that in English, psych, like
psychology, psychosis
has to do with your mind.
That's right. All right.
So psychic uses their
mind to find out things
about you or your future.
That's right. So sometimes
psychics will claim
that they can read
your mind as well. Right?
It's a little scary. So
as you say, these are
different, these are
people who supposedly can
tell you your future.
And as you said, they use
different methods
or different tools.
One of them is for example,
having your palms read.
All right. So the psychic
will go to you, Marco,
and we'll look at your hand
and we'll read your palm.
Now where on your
hand is your palm?
It's on the other side,
the side where you
grab things with the
inside. So the soft part.
Yes. And maybe on
your palm, you have many
different lines. So the
psychic will look at the
lines and we'll say, Oh,
well, this line is very long.
So you will have
a long, long life.
That's right. So supposedly
in your hands, you have
lines that determine how
much money you will have
or if you will, how many
kids you will have or
how long you will live.
So that's called a palm
reading or I am going
to have my palm read.
That's right. Now the
other person doesn't really
believe in all that stuff
and says that they are
just scam artists. So
he's saying that the side
gigs or the mediums
are just scam artists.
All right. So what
is a scam artist?
Well, a scam artist is not
a real artist. Right. Right.
A scam artist is a thief,
someone who will maybe tell
you a story or who
will lie to you to try and
take your money. That's
right. So he's not really
like a robber, like
somebody that will break into
your house and take your
things. No, he won't use a gun.
Maybe. Hopefully
not. But he will tell you
a story or will lie to
you in a way that makes
you want to give him
money. That's right.
That's right. So I don't
know if any of you have ever
received an email from
someone who said, I am a
wealthy person from a
different part of the world
and I want you to give
me money to help me so
I can come to America
and these kinds of things
where you don't know the
person he's probably lying to you.
It's a very sad
story. I say, please
give me money so I can
so I can come to visit you.
And we're so I can come
and have a good life.
That's a scam artist.
That's right. They probably
don't have a bad life.
They just want you to
give them money.
That's right. That's right.
So that is a scam artist.
And well, he went on
to say about how all of
these things about fortune
telling about psychics
and everything is just
superstitious nonsense.
So then the girl went on
to explain and saying
that it's not really true
that many cultures do
things like, for example,
read the tarot cards.
All right. So we had palm
reading first, maybe talking
to dead people with a medium.
But this is another tool that psychics used
to communicate with maybe the dead or to
understand the future.
So we have tarot cards and
they're actually cards,
you know, like playing
cards, but they're a
little bit different, right?
They don't have
diamonds and hearts.
They have different pictures.
Right. They have pictures
of, for example, a king
or a queen or a picture
of a river or different
symbols that basically
the person who is
getting their fortune read
will take it and move
them and shuffle them.
And then we'll start
flipping the cards over and
then you will see supposedly
what your future will be like.
All right. So those
are tarot cards.
But we have one more
word here and it actually
comes from the friend who
doesn't believe in these scam artists.
Right. It calls it all
superstitious nonsense.
That's right. So a person
that is superstitious believes
in superstitions and those
are beliefs of good or bad luck.
Yeah, that's right. So if I believe
that the number 13 is very,
very bad, I will
avoid the number 13.
I won't sit down and chair
number 13. I won't buy a house
on floor number 13. Right.
Because I'm superstitious.
I believe that that
number is bad luck.
That's right. So many
people believe that it's bad
luck to break a mirror
or to walk under a ladder.
Yes, also many
Americans believe it's bad
luck to open an umbrella
inside. That's right.
So it's interesting because
many cultures around
the world have different
types of superstitions,
but we'll talk about
that in a little bit.
Why don't we move on now to some fluency
builder and take a look at some phrases.
Look at this newspaper article
about this famous local medium.
It says that she
is really gifted
and so popular now that she's booked solid
with appointments for the next 12 months.
You don't really believe in all that
hocus pocus mumbo jumbo, do you?
Well, I have had many
friends that went to a
psychic and got their
poems read and most of the
things the psychic
told them came true.
Of course it does. They
tell you general and obvious
things like that you'll be
successful or have a big house.
I think most of
the times they're
just scam artists. Well, historically,
it's a practice that many cultures share,
reading the tarot cards and the
east, they would even read tea leaves.
I even heard that there
are people that make
you smoke a cigar and
then read your ashes.
All superstitious
nonsense. I would still like
to go to one and see what he
or she has to say just for kicks.
Great. I'll make an appointment.
All right, an important
phrase that you don't
have to be a psychic
to use is booked solid.
Now, we heard this in the
beginning of the dialogue.
Right, because this
person is so famous that so
many people want to go
there and get their fortunes
read that this person
is already booked solid
for the next 12 months.
Okay. Now, booked solid
is a very nice colloquial
way to describe having
no time for anything
in English. So basically,
if a restaurant, for
example, is booked solid,
it means there are
no tables available.
That's right. Nothing is available.
Everything is already reserved.
Yeah, it happens
also with hotels.
Some hotels during, I don't
know, let's say the Olympics,
many of them are booked
solid for the entire month.
Or you could even say
this with your friends,
you say, hey, Marko, do you
want to hang out Thursday,
say seven o'clock? Sorry, I'm
booked solid the entire day.
Popular guy. That's right.
So you can say that a person
is booked solid or that a
business is booked
solid. Now, this, this next
phrase is kind of more,
it's not really real words,
but we say they are,
hocus pocus mumbo jumbo.
All right, hocus pocus is a
way to describe superstitious
things like magic, right?
Because I think it comes
from supposedly, it's
a spell that witches or
wizards will say, you
know, like hocus pocus and
things like whatever
could Deborah, hocus. Yeah,
yeah, but basically, this is something that
we say when we're joking now in English.
So I'll say, oh gosh, Marco, I just
broke this mirror seven years bad luck.
Do you really believe
in all that hocus pocus?
Yes, I'm very superstitious.
So hocus pocus
here means superstitious
magic superstitious stuff.
It's all hocus pocus. What
about mumbo jumbo?
mumbo jumbo is also something
we say when we're talking
about magic or things
that are superstitious.
So I can say, I don't believe in any
of that superstitious mumbo jumbo.
It means basically, I don't trust it. I
don't think it's true. I think it's silly.
Right. So mumbo jumbo,
you referred to that
nonsense, that irrational
or unbelievable stuff.
That's right. It's
irrational. Very good.
So hocus pocus, referring
to magic, mumbo jumbo,
referring to superstition
or things that are not
really believable, let's say.
And to end the dialogue,
the guy says, well,
you know what?
Okay, let's go to this psychic and
see what she has to say just for kicks.
Just for kicks.
Now, I love this phrase. I
use it a lot. It's very, very
colloquial, very spoken English.
So you guys should try to use it.
It means just for
fun, just for fun.
So I'm not going
because I believe, right,
because I just said, I think it's
hocus pocus, mumbo jumbo.
Right. But I do think it will
be fun. So let's go just for kicks.
Mm hmm, just for kicks. Yeah. So it means
that you're doing something not seriously.
You're just doing it
for fun. That's right.
So you can do anything
just for kicks, really.
Maybe like, if you just sit
down and start doing some math
problems, just for kicks.
Yeah, you would do that,
wouldn't you work
or just for kicks? Yeah.
Or I'm going to take a
singing class just for kicks,
even though I don't
take singing very seriously.
Right. It's not like
you want to become a
professional singer. You
just want to do it for fun.
That's right. All
right. Great stuff.
Why don't we review
everything one last time?
Look at this newspaper article
about this famous local medium.
It says that she
is really gifted
and so popular now that she's booked solid
with appointments for the next 12 months.
You don't really believe in all that
hocus, pocus, mumbo jumbo, do you?
Well, I have had many
friends that went to a
psychic and got their
poems read and most of the
things the psychic
told them came true.
Of course it does. They tell
you general and obvious things
like that you'll be successful
or have a big house.
I think most of the times
they're just scam artists.
Well, historically,
it's a practice
that many cultures share,
reading the tarot cards
and the east, they would
even read tea leaves.
I even heard that there
are people that make
you smoke a cigar and
then read your ashes.
All superstitious nonsense.
I would still like to go
to one and see what he or
she has to say just for kicks.
Great. I'll make an appointment.
All right. So speaking
about superstitions, as
you said, some
superstitions are more local.
Like, for example, I think
it's Americans, I believe
it's bad luck to open an
umbrella inside a house.
Yes. I know that, for
example, in China,
it's the number four
is considered bad luck.
That's right. So
you'll see that many
buildings don't have a
floor number four or 14.
That's right. And actually,
it's similar in Western
cultures because some
hotels will not have a
floor 13. That's right. Are there any
superstitions that are from Ecuador?
I think Hispanic, oh,
there is one that's very
particular with women
with Hispanic women.
They will not put their bags,
their purses on the floor.
Yes, I've heard this before.
What is it? Your money will fly away.
Your money will fall out
or your money will go away.
So women will not put their their bags or
their purses on the floor. That's why you
will always put it on
a chair or on the table.
Never, never on the floor.
They're very superstitious about this.
Very interesting. Well, have you ever
had your fortune told by a psychic?
No, no, I've never,
I've seen gypsies.
So gypsies are people that
don't really live somewhere.
They don't settle anywhere.
They move around.
They go from city to city.
And I've seen them and
they've approached me that
asking me if I want my fortune read.
But I don't really
believe in that.
So I just seems like they
wanted me to give them
five dollars and they
would just tell me anything.
I think it was mumbo jumbo.
Have you had your fortune read?
I've had tarot cards read
for me. So to be honest,
I don't really remember
what my fortune was.
I don't remember if it
was right or not right.
But I do remember feeling
very uncomfortable because
the things that my, and I don't believe in
these things because I'm not superstitious.
But the things that the
fortune teller told me
I thought were interesting
because they were
very similar to things that I knew
about myself. So I don't know.
Yeah, some people, it's
interesting because some
people will go to a
fortune teller just for kicks
and will actually agree or find it
amazing what the fortune teller told them.
And other people aren't
really just not really interested.
But it's very, very, it's very
closely related to different cultures.
Some people have witch
doctors that also will, you know,
cleanse you or tell you
your future and stuff like that.
That's right. So we're actually very
curious to hear about your culture.
Do you have superstitions
in your culture and
are there traditional
forms of fortune telling?
Let us know our website is EnglishPod.com.
All right, guys. We'll see you there. Bye.